<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2013 Mirantis, Inc.

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
   implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                          http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink.xsd"
         version="5.0">
    <title>Quantum Usage</title>
    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>Murano does support both Nova Network and Quantum, and support advanced network management in case of
            Quantum. Advanced network management essentially means explicit (from Murano point of view) network
            management per environment. Murano creates private network and attache it to the first found external
            network for each environment. This functionality is based on Quantum deployed as
            <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/network-admin/admin/content/use_cases_mixed.html">Per-tenant
                Routers with Private Networks</link> and not going to work when Quantum is deployed as
            <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/network-admin/admin/content/use_cases_mixed.html">Mixed Flat and
                Private Network</link>.
        </para>
        <para><emphasis>Mixed Flat and Private Network</emphasis> supported in Nova Network and it is default configuration for
            Murano v0.3.
        </para>
        <para>With advanced networking schemes like <emphasis>Per-tenant Routers with Private Networks</emphasis> additional configuration and patches for OpenStack components
            are required. Different set of templates for Heat stacks is used in Murano Conductor.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Patching Murano</title>
        <para>To enable support for advanced network management in Murano we need to replace default templates for
            Heat stacks used in Murano Conductor. All necessary templates available in our git repository:</para>
        <screen>
git clone http://github.com/stackforge/murano-deployment
git checkout 0.3
        </screen>
        <para>Templates for Heat stacks are located in <emphasis>data</emphasis> directory. Please, overwrite them with
        content of <emphasis>quantum_support/conductor/data/templates/cf</emphasis> directory checked out above.</para>
        <screen>
cp -r quantum_support/conductor/data/* /etc/murano/data/
        </screen>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Patching OpenStack</title>
        <para>OpenStack Grizzly missing a few features that already implemented in the latest Havana release, or merged
        to Icehouse. We ported that features to OpenStack Grizzly and they available as set of .patch files. In order to
        use advanced network management we need to apply that patches ether to sources or to already installed packages.
        </para>
        <para>All necessary patches are available in our git repository:</para>
        <screen>
git clone http://github.com/stackforge/murano-deployment
git checkout 0.3
cd quantum_support/patches
        </screen>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring Quantum</title>
        <section>
            <title>Allow subnet ip-range overlapping</title>
            <para>
                When deploying environments, Murano will create dedicated network for each of them, and every such network will have a subnet created.
                All these subnets will have identical ip-ranges. Theoretically this is perfectly fine, as these subnets belong to different isolated Networks
                (L2 segments) and are connected to different routers.
            </para>
            <para>
                However, by default Quantum does not allow overlapping IPs for different subnets - even in different Networks.
                To override this restriction, change <filename>/etc/quantum/quantum.conf</filename>: uncomment <filename>allow_overlapping_ips</filename> parameter
                and change its value to <filename>True</filename>:
            </para>
            <programlisting>
[DEFAULT]
...
# Enable or disable overlapping IPs for subnets
# Attention: the following parameter MUST be set to False if Neutron is
# being used in conjunction with nova security groups
allow_overlapping_ips = True
            </programlisting>
            <para>
                Then, restart all quantum services:
            </para>
            <screen>
cd /etc/init.d/
for q in quantum-*; do restart $q; done
            </screen>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Known Issues</title>
        <para>Internet Information Services Web Farm &amp; ASP.NET Application Web Farm services does not work when
            Murano configured to support <emphasis>Per-tenant Routers with Private Networks</emphasis>. This services are
            based on Heat, particularly on resource called AWS::ElasticLoadBalancing::LoadBalancer, that currently does
            not support specification of any network related parameters. Without support for network configuration
            specification LoadBalancer does not work on OpenStack deployments with Quantum deployed as
            <emphasis>Per-tenant Routers with Private Networks</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
