<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 Copyright (c) 2013 Mirantis, Inc.

 Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
 implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                          http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink.xsd"
      version="5.0">
    <title>About Murano</title>
    <para>
        Murano Project introduces an application catalog, which allows application developers
        and cloud administrators to publish various cloud-ready applications in a browsable
        categorised catalog, which may be used by the cloud users (including the unexperienced ones)
        to pick-up the needed applications and services and composes the reliable environments out of
        them in a “push-the-button” manner. Key goal is to provide UI and API which allows to compose
        and deploy composite environments on the Application abstraction level and then manage their
        lifecycle. The Service should be able to orchestrate complex circular dependent cases in order
        to setup complete environments with many dependant applications and services. However, the
        actual deployment itself will be done by the existing software orchestration tools (such as Heat),
        while the Murano project will become an integration point for various applications and services.
    </para>
    <para>
        The service addresses following use cases:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Self-deploying of predefined Services with their dependencies</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Automation of administrative tasks during data center roll-out</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Custom windows application as a Windows Service</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Custom linux application as a Linux Service</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        The solution provides higher level of abstraction for manipulation applications. Key concepts are:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows Service - a service such as Active Directory, MsSQL, or IIS, which usually consists of multiple virtual machines (VM) and has multiple dependencies.
                </para>
            </listitem>
             <listitem>
                <para>Linux Service - a service such as Apache Server can be easily preconfigured and installed in 1-Click
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Environment - a logical unit for one or several Services.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>VM instance - a VM which hosts a Service. A Service might be deployed over several VM instances.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Metadata Service - Service that provides opportunity to manage custom services definitions.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        The Key Features of the Service are the following:
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Native to OpenStack</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Introduces abstraction level for Windows Environments</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Supports Availability Zones and Disaster Recovery scenarios</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Uses native Windows features for High Availability (HA) solutions</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
            </para>
    <section>
        <title>Document change history</title>
        <para>The following table describes the most recent changes:</para>
        <informaltable rules="all" frame="all">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td align="center" colspan="1">Revision Date</td>
                    <td align="center" colspan="3">Version of Murano</td>
                    <td align="center" colspan="4">Summary of Changes</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td colspan="1" align="center">  September. 4, 2013  </td>
                    <td colspan="3" align="center">  Release-0.2  </td>
                    <td colspan="4">
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Initial document creation.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td colspan="1" align="center">  December. 9, 2013  </td>
                    <td colspan="3" align="center">  Release-0.4  </td>
                    <td colspan="4">
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Update with Release-0.4 information</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                 <tr>
                    <td colspan="1" align="center">  February. 9, 2014  </td>
                    <td colspan="3" align="center">  Release-0.4.1  </td>
                    <td colspan="4">
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Update with Release-0.4.1 information</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </informaltable>
    </section>

</chapter>
